and I'm a black, Muslim, Somali-American from Kenya. (Applause) Some have called me a trailblazer -- I was the first Muslim homecoming queen at my high school, the first Somali student senator at my college and the first hijab-wearing woman in many places, like the Miss Minnesota USA beauty pageant, the runways of Milan and New York Fashion Weeks and even on the historic cover of British "Vogue." As you can see, I'm not afraid to be the first, to step out on my own, to take risks and seek change, because that's what being a minority is about. It's about using yourself as a vessel to create change and being a human representation for the power of diversity. And now I use my platform to spread an important message of acceptance. But it hasn't always been easy. When we first arrived to the United States and made St. Louis, Missouri home, I remember asking my mom, "Is this really America?" There were things that were sadly familiar, like hearing gunshots at night and the streets looking impoverished. But there were things that were also very different. Like when I started first grade, I noticed how the kids played in groups. In America, we call them "cliques." Back here, we all played together. Gender didn't matter, and race most certainly never mattered. I remember asking myself, "Why don't they understand Swahili? Swahili is the language that brings people together." To make matters worse, the school I was enrolled in didn't have an English immersion program. So everyday I would get up, go to school, sit in my desk and never learn a thing. This is when I started losing hope, and I wanted nothing more than return to Kakuma, a refugee camp. Soon, my mother learned that many Somalis found refuge in a small town in Minnesota. So when I was eight, we moved to Minnesota. My life changed as I met other students who spoke Somali, attended a school that had an English immersion program and found teachers that would go above and beyond, staying there after school hours and lunch breaks, dedicated to helping me find success in the classroom. Being a child refugee has taught me that one could be stripped of everything: food, shelter, clean drinking water, even friendship, but the one thing that no one could ever take away from you is your education. So I made studying my top priority and soon started flourishing within the classroom. As I grew older, I became more aware of others and how they viewed my race and background. Specifically, when I started wearing the head scarf known as a hijab. When I first started wearing it, I was excited. I remember admiring my mother's, and I wanted to emulate her beauty. But when I started middle school, the students teased me about not having hair, so to prove them wrong, I started showing them my hair -- something that goes against my beliefs, but something I felt pressured to do. I wanted so badly to fit in at the time. When I reflect on the issues of race, religion, identity, a lot of painful memories come to mind. It would be easy for me to blame those of another culture for making me feel the pain I felt, but when I think deeper, I also recognize that the most impactful, positive, life-changing events that have happened to me are thanks to those people who are different than me. It was at this moment that I decided to step outside of my comfort zone and compete in a pageant wearing a hijab and burkini. I saw it as an opportunity to be a voice for women who, like myself, had felt underrepresented. And although I didn't capture the crown, that experience opened so many doors for me. I was receiving emails and messages from women all over the world, telling me that I've inspired them by simply staying true to myself. The other "firsts" kept coming. I was invited to New York City by fashion icon Carine Roitfeld to shoot my very first editorial. It was around this time that I became the first hijab-wearing model, and in my first year, I graced the covers of nine fashion magazines. It was a whirlwind, to say the least. But with all the overnight success, there was one thing that remained constant -- the thought that this could be what brings me back here to Kakuma, the place that I call home. And just a few months ago, something incredible happened to me. I was in New York City, on a photo shoot, when I met South Sudanese model Adut Akech, who also happened to be born right here in Kakuma. That experience in itself is the definition of hope. I mean, just imagine: two girls born in the same refugee camp, reunited for the first time on the cover of British "Vogue." (Applause and cheering) I was given the distinct pleasure of partnering up with UNICEF, knowing firsthand the work that they do for children in need. And I want you to remember that although the children here may be refugees, they are children. They deserve every opportunity to flourish, to hope, to dream -- to be successful. My story began right here in Kakuma refugee camp, a place of hope. Thank you. (Applause)
y soy una somalí-estadounidense musulmana y de color, procedente de Kenia. (Aplauso) Dicen que soy una pionera, fui la primera reina musulmana del baile de mi bachillerato, la primera senadora somalí estudiantil en mi universidad y la primera mujer en portar el hiyab en muchos sitios, como en el concurso de belleza de Señorita Minnesota en EE. UU. las pasarelas de Milán y las Semanas de la Moda de Nueva York, e incluso en la histórica portada de la "Vogue" británica. Como ven, no me preocupa ser la primera y salir por mi cuenta, arriesgarme y buscar el cambio porque en eso consiste ser minoría. Se trata de usarse a sí mismo para propiciar un cambio y de ser una representante humana del poder de la diversidad. Ahora, utilizo mi posición para difundir un importante mensaje de aceptación. Pero no siempre ha sido fácil. Cuando llegamos a EE. UU., hicimos de St. Louis, Missouri, nuestro hogar, me acuerdo de que le pregunté a mi madre: "¿De verdad esto es EE. UU.?". Había cosas que me resultaban tristemente familiares, como oír disparos por la noche o las calles de aspecto empobrecido. Pero también había cosas que eran muy diferentes, como cuando empecé la primaria. Noté que los niños jugaban en grupos. En EE. UU., lo llaman "pandillas". Aquí, todos jugábamos juntos. Tu sexo no importaba, y tu raza, sin lugar a dudas, tampoco. Recuerdo que me preguntaba: "¿Por qué no entienden suajili? El suajili es el idioma que une a los pueblos". Para colmo de males, el colegio en el yo estaba no tenía ningún programa de inmersión en inglés. Así que todos los días, me levantaba, iba al colegio, me sentaba en mi pupitre y no aprendía nada. Ahí empecé a perder la esperanza y solo deseaba regresar a Kakuma, al campo de refugiados. Pronto, mi madre descubrió que muchos somalíes hallaron asilo en un pueblecito de Minnesota. Y cuando cumplí ocho años, nos mudamos a Minnesota. Mi vida cambió en cuanto conocí a otros estudiantes que hablaban somalí, fui a un colegio con un programa de inmersión en inglés y encontré profesores que hacían lo imposible, se quedaban después de clases y en los recreos, dedicados a ayudarme a triunfar en clase. Ser una niña refugiada me enseñó que a uno podían despojarlo de todo: de la comida, de la vivienda, del agua potable, incluso de la amistad, pero lo único que nadie podría quitarnos jamás sería la educación. Así que mi prioridad principal fueron los estudios y pronto, comencé a prosperar en clase. A medida que fui creciendo, tomé conciencia de otras personas y de lo que opinaban de mi raza y de mi pasado. Específicamente, cuando empecé a portar el velo en la cabeza llamado hiyab. Cuando empecé a usarlo, estaba emocionada. Recuerdo cómo admiraba el de mi madre y quería emular su hermosura. Pero cuando comencé la secundaria, los alumnos se burlaban y me decían que no tenía cabello, y para demostrarles lo contrario, les enseñaba mi cabello, lo cual va en contra de mis creencias, pero me sentí presionada a hacerlo. Yo quería encajar con todas mis fuerzas. Al reflexionar sobre cuestiones de raza, religión o identidad, me vienen a la mente muchos recuerdos dolorosos. Podría acusar fácilmente a los de otras culturas de hacerme sentir ese dolor, pero pensándolo bien, también reconozco que los hechos más impactantes, positivos y que cambiaron mi vida, me ocurrieron gracias a toda esa gente que es diferente a mí. Fue entonces cuando decidí salir de mi zona de confort y competí en un certamen portando el hiyab y el burkini. Lo vi como una oportunidad para hablar por las mujeres que, como yo, no se sentían representadas. Y aunque no conseguí la corona, esa experiencia me abrió muchas puertas. Recibí correos y mensajes de mujeres de todo el mundo diciéndome que mi autenticidad les había servido de inspiración. Otros "debuts" siguieron llegando. Carine Roitfeld, icono de la moda, me invitó a Nueva York para rodar mi primera sesión de editorial. En esa época me convertí en la primera modelo con hiyab y en mi primer año, adorné las portadas de nueve revistas de moda. Fue sensacional, por decir algo. Pero a pesar de ese éxito tan repentino, hubo algo que no cambió: la idea de poder regresar aquí a Kakuma, el lugar al que llamo mi hogar. Y tan solo unos meses después, me sucedió algo increíble. Estaba en Nueva York, en una sesión de fotos, cuando conocí a la modelo sursudanesa Adut Akech quien también nació aquí en Kukuma. Esa experiencia en sí, es la mejor definición de esperanza. Imagínense, dos niñas que nacieron en el mismo campo de refugiados se juntan por primera vez en la portada de la "Vogue" británica. (Aplauso y ovación) Tuve el gran honor de asociarme con UNICEF sabiendo de primera mano el trabajo que hacen por los niños necesitados. Quisiera que se acuerden de que los niños aquí refugiados, siguen siendo niños. Se merecen todas las oportunidades para prosperar, tener esperanza, soñar y triunfar. Mi historia comenzó justo aquí, en el campo de refugiados de Kakuma, un lugar de esperanza. Gracias. (Aplauso)